안녕하세요.
Hello.
Talk To Me In Korean의 이야기입니다.
안녕하세요.
최경은입니다.
This is Talk To Me In Korean's Iyagi.
Hello.
I'm Kyeong-eun Choi.
진석진입니다.
I'm Seok-jin Jin.
네, 이야기 세 번째 시간입니다.
Yes, this is our third Iyagi episode.
석진 씨, 안녕하세요?
Seok-jin, hello.
네, 안녕하세요.
Yes, hello.
벌써 세 번째에요.
It's already the third one.
네, 벌써 세 번째 시간인데요.
Yes, it's already the third episode.
한국 사람한테 3이라는 숫자가 아주 의미가 있는 것 같아요.
It seems like the number 3 is very meaningful to Koreans.
의미가 있다고요?
Did you say it's meaningful?
네.
Yes.
어떤 의미가 있죠?
What kind of meaning does it have?
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
음… 하루에 밥을 세끼 먹잖아요?
Well... we eat three meals a day, don't we?
네.
Yes.
밥을 세 번 먹죠.
We eat three times.
네.
Yes.
가위바위보를 할 때도 삼세판이란 말도 있고요.
Even when we play Rock-Paper-Scissors, there's a saying "sam-se-pan" (best of three).
세 번을 해서, 세 번을 먼저 이긴 사람이 승자가 되는 거죠.
You play three times, and the person who wins three times first becomes the winner.
네, 맞아요.
Yes, that's right.
석진 씨는 그러면 숫자들 중에서 3이 젤 좋아요?
Then Seok-jin, is 3 your favorite out of all numbers?
네.
Yes.
저 3 좋고요.
I like 3.
13도 좋아요.
I like 13 too.
13이요?
13?
네.
Yes.
13은 안 좋은 숫자 아니에요?
Isn't 13 an unlucky number?
네.
Yes.
미국에서는 좀 안 좋은 숫자인데요?
In America, it's considered a bit of an unlucky number, right?
13일의 금요일.
Friday the 13th.
그런 영화도 있잖아요?
There's even a movie like that, isn't there?
그런데 제가 좋아하는 선수,
But a player I like,
박지성 선수의 등 번호가 13번 이라서
Park Ji-sung's jersey number is 13,
제가 13번을 정말 좋아해요.
so I really like the number 13.
아 ...
Oh...
그렇군요 ...
I see...
그런데 석진 씨 오늘 우리 숫자에 대해서 이야기하나요?
By the way Seok-jin, are we talking about numbers today?
아니요.
No.
경은 씨.
Kyeong-eun.
네.
Yes.
경은 씨.
Kyeong-eun.
네.
Yes.
경은 씨?
Kyeong-eun?
네?
Yes?
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
지금 스트레스 쌓이죠?
Your stress is building up right now, isn't it?
계속 부르니까 스트레스 쌓이죠?
Because I keep calling you, your stress is building up, right?
네.
Yes.
석진 씨.
Seok-jin.
그만 좀 불러요.
Stop calling me.
왜 이렇게 귀찮게 불러요.
Why are you annoying me by calling me like this.
오늘 주제가 스트레스잖아요.
Today's topic is stress, you see.
아, 오늘의 주제가?
Ah, today's topic is?
스트레스.
Stress.
스트레스 쌓이는 거에 대한 주제인가요?
Is the topic about stress building up?
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
아니요.
No.
스트레스를 어떻게 하면 잘 풀 수 있을까.
It's about how we can relieve stress well.
네.
Yes.
그것에 대해서 이야기해 봐요.
Let's talk about that.
아, 좋아요.
Ah, sounds good.
풀 수 있는 석진 씨만의 방법이 있나요?
Is there a method unique to you, Seok-jin, to relieve it?
스트레스에는 한 가지만 있는 게 아니에요.
For stress, there isn't just one type.
일이 너무 많아서 힘들 때
When it's tough because there's too much work,
또 여자친구가 없어서 외로워서 생기는 그 스트레스
or the stress that comes from being lonely because you don't have a girlfriend.
네.
Yes.
그리고 부모님이 보고 싶어서
And because you miss your parents.
네.
Yes.
석진씨는 지금 부모님하고 따로 떨어져 살죠?
Seok-jin, you currently live apart from your parents, right?
그렇죠.
That's right.
부모님 보러 가려면 한 4시간을 차를 타야 돼요.
To go see my parents, I have to ride in a car for about 4 hours.
네.
Yes.
그런 그리움이 있어요.
There's that kind of longing.
네.
Yes.
그런 그리움 때문에 나오는 스트레스가 따로 있는데 먼저 나오는 스트레스를
The stress that comes from that longing is different, but first, I'll tell you how I relieve the stress that comes up first.
어떻게 푸는지 알려 드리겠어요.
그 스트레스 종류에 따라서 푸는 방법이 다 달라요?
So the method of relieving it is completely different depending on the type of stress?
다르죠 ...
It's different...
네, 말해 주세요.
Yes, please tell me.
네.
Yes.
일이 많았을 때는 그때 그때 잘 풀어 줘야 돼요.
When there's a lot of work, you have to relieve it right then and there.
그러니까 어떻게 그때 그때 잘 풀죠?
So, how exactly do you relieve it well right then and there?
네.
Yes.
한국에는 지금 노래방이 정말 많아요.
In Korea right now, there are really a lot of noraebangs (karaoke rooms).
저 노래 부르는 거 정말 좋아하거든요.
I really like singing, you see.
아 ...
Ah...
그래요?
Really?
네.
Yes.
노래방을 갑니다.
I go to a noraebang.
그리고 신나는 노래
And an exciting song,
네.
Yes.
소리를 막 지를 수 있는 그런 노래를 골라서
I choose a song where I can just scream out loud,
노브레인이라는 밴드가 있어요.
there's a band called No Brain.
사실 저희 Talk To Me In Korean을 들으시는 많은 분들은 한국 노래를 굉장히 좋아하잖아요.
Actually, many people who listen to our Talk To Me In Korean really like Korean songs, don't they?
그렇죠.
That's true.
노래방도 굉장히 좋아하실 것 같은데
I think they would really like noraebangs too,
노래방에 가서 그런 노래를 부르는 게 스트레스를 푸는 데 도움이 많이 되는 군요?
so going to a noraebang and singing those kinds of songs helps a lot in relieving stress?
네.
Yes.
한 시간 동안 노래를 딱 부르고 나면, 기분이 정말 좋아져요.
After singing for exactly one hour, my mood gets really good.
진석진 씨 혹시 그런 사람 아니에요?
Seok-jin, by any chance, aren't you that kind of person?
노래방에서 꼴불견 1위, 마이크를 절대 놓지 않는다.
The number 1 eyesore at a noraebang: the person who never lets go of the microphone.
그래서 전 혼자 가요.
That's why I go alone.
최경은:
Kyeong-eun Choi:
혼자 노래방에 간 적도 있어요?
Have you ever been to a noraebang alone?
두 명 까지는 가 봤는데 최경은:
I've gone with up to two people, but... Kyeong-eun Choi:
혼자 간 적은 없어요?
You've never gone alone?
혼자 간 적은 아직 없어요.
I haven't gone alone yet.
최경은:
Kyeong-eun Choi:
어, 다행이네요.
Oh, thank goodness.
그런 적 있어요.
I have done something like this.
집에서 노래 반주를 켜 놓고
At home, turning on a karaoke accompaniment,
혼자 이불을 뒤집어 쓰고 부른 적 있어요.
pulling the blanket over my head and singing alone before.
아 ...
Ah...
그거는 괜찮을 것 같아요.
I think that would be fine.
저는.
For me.
저는 사실 노래를 못 해서 노래방 가는 걸 싫어하거든요.
I actually can't sing, so I hate going to noraebangs.
언제, 경은 씨 노래 한번 듣고 싶은데, 최경은:
Someday, I want to hear you sing, Kyeong-eun. Kyeong-eun Choi:
아우, 저는 싫어합니다.
Oh, I hate that.
진석진 씨가 불러 주세요.
You sing for me, Seok-jin.
언제?
Someday?
최경은:
Kyeong-eun Choi:
지금.
Right now.
지금이요?
Right now?
네.
Yes.
아유,
Oh dear,
여자 앞에서는 조금 감미로운 노래를 불러야 되는데 최경은:
in front of a woman, I should sing a slightly sweet song, but... Kyeong-eun Choi:
석진 씨가 지금 노래 부르면 스트레스가 풀릴 것 같아요.
If you sing right now, Seok-jin, I think my stress will be relieved.
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
지금 화났어요?
Are you angry right now?
지금 스트레스 쌓여요?
Is your stress building up right now?
요즘에 조금 피곤해서 스트레스가 많이 쌓였거든요.
I've been a bit tired lately, so a lot of stress has built up.
저는 사실 노래를 부르는 것보다 노래 들으면서 스트레스를 많이 풀어요.
I actually relieve stress more by listening to music rather than singing.
제가 좋아하는 노래를 들으면 스트레스가 많이 풀리더라고요.
When I listen to songs I like, my stress gets relieved a lot.
그러니까 불러 주세요.
That's why, please sing for me.
"있을 때 잘 해,
"Treat me well while I'm here,
후회하지 말고 ,"
don't regret it later,"
저 있을 때 잘 해 주세요.
Please treat me well while I'm here.
다른 스트레스를 푸는 방법은 뭐가 있죠?
What other methods are there to relieve stress?
두 번째 스트레스.
The second stress.
외로워서.
Being lonely.
여자 친구가 없어서.
Because you don't have a girlfriend.
그런 외로움.
That kind of loneliness.
보통 여자친구가 없을 때
Usually, when they don't have a girlfriend,
보통
usually,
여자친구들한테 친한 친구들한테 전화 거는 사람들이 많아요.
there are many people who make phone calls to their female friends or close friends.
특히 밤 늦은 시간에.
Especially late at night.
그러면 안되죠.
You shouldn't do that.
그러면 여자들이 스트레스를 받겠죠?
Then women would get stressed, right?
네, 정말 그런 건 안 좋아요.
Yes, that's really not good.
그럴 때는 다른 방법이 없어요.
In that case, there is no other way.
그냥 자야 돼요.
You just have to sleep.
네,
Yes,
다른 사람들한테 피해 주지 말고
without causing trouble to other people,
그냥 하룻밤 딱 자고 나면 그 다음날 이런 생각을 하죠.
if you just sleep for one night, the next day you think like this:
'아, 참 전화 안 하길 정말 잘했다.'
'Ah, I'm really glad I didn't call.'
네.
Yes.
석진 씨.
Seok-jin.
저한테 전화하지 말고 좀 자요?
Don't call me, just go to sleep, okay?
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
그래도 제가 전화할 때가 경은 씨 밖에 없는데 ...
Still, Kyeong-eun, you're the only one I have to call...
최경은:
Kyeong-eun Choi:
알겠습니다.
I understand.
그리고요?
And?
다른 방법은요?
What about other methods?
네, 엄마가 보고 싶을 때.
Yes, when you miss your mom.
부모님이 보고 싶을 때는 한 번 울어 주세요.
When you miss your parents, cry just once.
한국에서는 근데 남자들이 울면 안 좋다라는 이야기가 많잖아요.
But in Korea, there's a lot of talk saying it's not good if men cry.
터프한 남자는 절대 울면 안 된다.
A tough man must never cry.
네.
Yes.
터프한 남자는 절대 울지 않습니다.
A tough man never cries.
특히 남이 보는 데서 울지 않습니다.
Especially, he does not cry where others can see.
아,
Ah,
집에서 혼자
alone at home,
이불 뒤집어 쓰고 많이 울었나요?
did you cry a lot pulling the blanket over your head?
군대 있을 때 많이 울었어요.
I cried a lot when I was in the military.
부모님 보고 싶어서?
Because you missed your parents?
네.
Yes.
한번 전화 걸었는데
I called them once,
부모님 앞에서 울기는 좀 그렇고, 그냥 전화를 끊고 나서 좀 울었었죠.
but crying in front of my parents was a bit much, so I just hung up the phone and cried for a bit.
이렇게 우는 게 좋은 이유는 한 번 울고 나면 정말 힘이 생겨요.
The reason why crying like this is good is because after you cry once, you really gain strength.
네.
Yes.
개운해지고 다음에 더 힘을 낼 수 있는 그런 힘이 생기는 것 같아요.
You feel refreshed, and I think it gives you the kind of strength to do better next time.
네, 경은 씨는?
Yes, what about you, Kyeong-eun?
저는 그냥 단순하게 스트레스 받으면 자요.
For me, simply, when I get stressed, I sleep.
많이 자고요.
I sleep a lot.
그리고 음 ...
And, well...
맛있는 음식 먹으러 갈 때도 있고요.
There are times when I go to eat delicious food, too.
저는 진짜 맛있는 음식 먹으면 스트레스가 많이 풀리는 것 같아요.
I think my stress is relieved a lot when I eat truly delicious food.
그래서 요즘 경은 씨가 ...
That's why lately, Kyeong-eun...
네 ...
Yes...
좀 ...
A bit...
아, 살이 쪘어요?
Ah, did I gain weight?
운동하겠습니다.
I will exercise.
석진 씨 때문에 스트레스 받는 거예요.
I'm getting stressed because of you, Seok-jin.
살쪘다고 말하지 마세요.
Don't say I gained weight.
네, 죄송합니다.
Yes, I'm sorry.
그리고 맛있는 음식도 먹고,
And besides eating delicious food,
여자들은 보통 친구들하고 수다를 떨면서 스트레스를 풀잖아요?
women usually relieve stress by chatting with friends, right?
저도 마찬가지로 친구들 만나서 이야기하고,
Same for me, I meet friends and talk,
또 맛있는 음식 먹고 이러면서 스트레스 많이 풀고요.
and eat delicious food, and that's how I relieve a lot of stress.
그리고 좋은 책 골라서 읽으려고 노력하고.
And I try to choose and read good books.
그런 것들?
Things like that?
조금 어떻게 보면 평범한 것들인 것 같아요.
In a way, I think they are somewhat ordinary things.
음 ...
Um...
하지만 그런 평범한 게 가장 효율적인 거 아닐까요?
But wouldn't those ordinary things be the most efficient?
그럴 수도 있죠.
That could be true.
혹시 여러분들 중에서 자신만의 스트레스를 푸는 특별한 방법이 있으시면 저희한테 알려 주세요.
If any of you have your own special method for relieving stress, please let us know.
TalkToMeInKorean.com에 오셔서 코멘트로 저희에게 스트레스 푸는 방법을 꼭 알려 주세요.
Please come to TalkToMeInKorean.com and be sure to let us know your way of relieving stress in the comments.
네.
Yes.
경은 씨.
Kyeong-eun.
이따가 노래방 한번 갈까?
Shall we go to a noraebang together later?
아우 ...
Oh...
싫어요.
I don't want to.
가자.
Let's go.
맛있는 거 사 주세요.
Buy me something delicious.
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
맛있는 거 짜장면?
Something delicious, Jajangmyeon?
물론 짜장면 좋아하지만 다른 거 맛있는 거 사 주세요.
Of course I like Jajangmyeon, but buy me something else that is delicious.
다음에 석진 씨 노래 한 번 제대로 들려 주세요.
Next time, please let us hear you sing properly, Seok-jin.
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
Talk To Me In Korean에 나올 거예요?
Is it going to be on Talk To Me In Korean?
당연하죠?
Of course.
여러분들이 기대하고 있을 거예요.
Everyone will be looking forward to it.
진석진:
Seok-jin Jin:
네, 준비하겠습니다.
Yes, I will prepare.
네, 그러면 이야기 오늘도 ...
Yes, then Iyagi today as well...
지금 말고요.
Not right now.
석진 씨.
Seok-jin.
아 ...
Ah...
저 스트레스 받아요.
I'm getting stressed.
이거 클로징 ...
This closing...
클로징 노래인데.
It's a closing song, though.
아, 저희 좋은 클로징 음악 따로 있으니까 그만.
Ah, we have a separate, good closing music, so stop it.
알겠습니다.
I understand.
네, 들어 주셔서 감사하고요.
Yes, thank you for listening.
여러분 꼭 저희에게 이야기해 주세요.
Everyone, please be sure to talk to us.
네, 안녕히 계세요.
Yes, goodbye.
안녕히 계세요
Goodbye.